this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hey this is Jeremy John for a
software engineering radio today I'm
speaking with Michael Chen Michael chan
has been teaching Reax since 2013 and is
the host of the react podcast he
currently works at ministry centered
technologies as a front-end architect
I'll be speaking with Michael about
react when and how to introduce it and
navigating the react ecosystem Michael
welcome to software engineering radio
thank you so much for having me you have
such a wonderful lineup of guests on
this show I feel very honored to be
sitting here and talking with you today
awesome first I want to start with
defining what react is so in in your
words what is react oh man who is it
coming out with the big guns right off
the bat so react is a view library
effectively so it's a tool for building
out user interfaces so managing that
view layer and they give you one tool
which is the component and you can can
define components to make complex trees
of elements or just rap simple elements
they're pretty similar conceptually to
web components but they're very
different everything happens in react
they're all managed by react and
effectively they've done a lot of magic
to be able to make programming and react
very declarative so you create a tree
just in the same way that you create
like a HTML tree of elements and you
tell react hey insert this at this node
and from that point on react takes
control over everything all of the
updates so you know when state changes
and all that kind of stuff it will very
wisely and selectively make updates to
the Dom kind of very surgically and it
all comes together and it sounds you
know I've given a very complicated
introduction to it but
all very simple it feels a lot like
writing HTML in JavaScript and just
having all of those updates happen like
really quickly getting this really nice
model for defining your own types of
elements and it's um it's great but yeah
mostly just a view library you were
talking about how it has a declarative
interface could you kind of go a little
bit more into that like how does that
look compared to traditional web
development working with the Dom and
things like that yeah so this is a very
different kind of mindset from web
components I'd say this is one of the
biggest differences between react and
web components is web components is very
imperative you know when you define a
web component you're handling everything
you're telling you're telling the Dom
how to actually do the mutations to
update itself in react there's this one
function at the bottom of your
application and it will mount your react
application however big that is into a
single node on the Dom and so usually
the way react app looks is you'll have
like an HTML file and it'll have just a
single div with like ID root in it and
that's where react is going to to render
your application now this can be
something as simple as hello world or a
to-do app or a full-blown application so
this could be like facebook.com/ renders
a react app into that node and the the
difference with react is is that you get
to think about your application at like
any given point in time so because react
manages all of the state for you the
best way that I've found to describe it
is it feels a lot more like when we have
written server-side applications in the
past there's that kind of feeling where
it's like I am going to click this
button and I'm going to make a request
to the server and then I get a whole
page back right it's very similar to
that but it happens all in the client so
you click a button and then react is
going to do whatever action it was that
you you know that button does it's going
to redraw the full application but
instead of like reans
turning into the Dom which could be
dangerous because you'd lose like input
state you know if you had any transient
forms filled out anytime you updated
focus would get lost and all that bad
things would happen right react just
very carefully says it looks at you know
what has changed and what is currently
in the Dom and says okay these two
things are different so we're just gonna
insert those this one thing down here in
the corner it's not there anymore so
we're gonna take that out and it does
the minimal change set to to update the
Dom for you so instead of you saying
like okay do all of those things like
input insert this insert this remove
this react just does all of that for you
and it's just like you're just writing a
view just given the state that you have
and you just think about it in terms of
like what's happening at exactly any
given moment and I think that's the main
difference between like you know
declarative and imperative is how much
do you have to tell the Dom to do if I
understand correctly if we had let's say
a list of names in traditional Dom
development if we wanted to add a new
name to the list we would have to find
the Dom element that has all of these
all of these names in it and we would
have to find it by like an ID or a class
name and then we would append a new Dom
element to the end after we found the
correct element we wanted to append -
right yep yep and in Reax case we would
have a component and that component it
would take in a parameter that would be
that list of names right so let's say
Michael and David that's currently in
the list so we pass in Michael and David
as a parameter and then react would
figure out what HTML to output to the
browser based off of what we passed in
right yes so you would still define the
the HTML that that's going to get used
but then yeah react would kind of decide
how how any updates to that happen so if
you you you you write
render it first with with Michael and
David and then something happens you
know so now we add Jeremy to the list it
will now rebuild that that list but
instead of pulling that whole list and
inserting a new list which could could
be very large right you could have maybe
hundreds or thousands of items in that
list and that would be very slow on
it'll say like okay we already have
Michael and we already have David so
we're adding Jeremy so we're just gonna
do an insertion for Jeremy and you know
if you were programming this yourself
you would you would have to take take
efforts to make sure that that happened
so that it was you know performant but
in Reax case they've they've abstract it
away all of that and it just it just
kind of works like magic exactly like
you would want it to and the way that
you write the HTML within the react
component is using something called JSX
so could you kind of explain a little
bit about what JSX is and how that works
yeah JSX is one of the weirdest things
ever i it's it's like a really weird
like demonic HTML it looks a lot like
HTML it is an XML syntax for writing
functions which sounds really weird but
what it what it is is it allows you to
write that style that like HTML XML type
of style for these elements and react
inside of JavaScript so react happens
all in JavaScript planned unlike a
library is like view or I think angular
still does this definitely Ember
there are no templates so you know in
the past we've had like handlebar temp
or even currently we have a handlebar
templates or you know a view template
and they are effectively just strings of
HTML and they're these little you know
areas where we can interpolate things
and when we compile our our data to our
view templates those get get rendered
out and inserted into the Dom now react
is totally different it all happens in
in JavaScript there's no kind of like
compiling view templates and when you
create components your returning react
elements and these are just templates
for actual Dom elements so you're not
returning down elements you're returning
react elements and they tell react how
to draw the Dom elements and this all
gets like super confusing it's like the
just JavaScript thing is a little bit of
like a white lie in in react because as
mentioned JSX
kind of screws that all up a little bit
but react knows this function called
react create element and you can use
this in any react app that you want it's
it's what all react apps use but that
gets abstracted into in in typical apps
into JSX
so where you could say react dot create
element div and then give it some
parameters instead we use this syntax
called JSX which looks a lot like HTML
and you would just write angle bracket
div and then your parameters as
attributes and the way that is all
empowered is through babel transforms
and so every time it sees these angle
brackets it's like that's not javascript
so you tell babel like hey yeah that's
not javascript is JSX and when you see
those just turn it into this function
react dot create element and once you
get the hang of it it all kind of like
makes sense but if you don't really know
that that's what's happening under the
hood it looks super weird because it
looks like you just have a function
that's returning HTML which is
impossible as we all know and yes that's
that's what JSX is and it's not react
specific you could have JSX
you know by default and babel I think it
does react dot create element but you
could have that do any any function it
could you know run the function H or my
element or whatever you want yeah that's
GS X and it is I think the biggest
stumbling block to getting into react
because beyond looking funny there are a
bunch of kind of weird things like
instead of writing class for applying
style classes you would write class name
instead of for its like HTML for
again form elements so there's a lot of
kind of gotchas like right up front and
react with that with JSX so if you are
writing JSX you said it looks very
similar to HTML but what's actually
happening is it's taking this markup
that looks like HTML and it's compiling
it down to regular javascript codes so
instead of writing let's say a div tag
in HTML it's actually creating a
JavaScript function call that says react
dot create element div for example is
that is that correct yeah so it'll
actually create a bunch of objects and
so they're basically just blueprints for
what that element would look like and so
it would say like you know type is div
or whatever and then have you know the
attributes that would go on there and
see it doesn't do properties because
react has its own idea of props but yeah
any like kind of nested children and it
would just build up this big object of
all of these elements and then it would
use that to determine which elements
need to get inserted to the Dom which
ones have changed etc and what are some
of the the benefits of this approach
like what are the benefits of having it
generate JavaScript code versus the
template approach that you were
mentioning some other frameworks use
yeah that's a great question I know that
one of the things for me is just the
practical advantage of having my code
and my template in the same place I know
not not a lot of people like that but
I've found in front-end development I'm
typically changing my my view and that
you know controller or whatever it is
that feeds data to the view in tandem
and so I love that react puts those
together so for me personally there's a
practical advantage of having those Colo
cated I know that there's you know maybe
some some speed advantages is to not
parsing strings I couldn't speak to that
specifically because I'm not I'm not
that bright I I just make views but I
know that there's some you know some
theoretical speed
as to that I know that it's it's easier
to kind of like diff these objects
before they become become views but
that's a little bit outside of my depths
I couldn't speak knowledgeably to the to
the performance gains because I know
there's a lot of really cool stuff
happening in some of the other libraries
where they're pre compiling a lot of
those templates and turning them into
functions anyway so I couldn't speak to
that side of it I'm not sure of this has
changed recently but I remembered
working with things like angular one in
the past where you would write a HTML
template and if you would make a mistake
when you wrote the template then the
HTML once you actually looked at the
webpage you would just get nothing yeah
and you would have no idea like what was
wrong whereas I believe with react when
you write the JSX markup if you make a
mistake I think because it compiles down
to JavaScript the tooling can tell you
what kind of mistake you made yeah
definitely if you had if you have a
syntax error in any of these which is
that's that's a great point if you have
a syntax error it's a lot easier for
JavaScript to report that to you when
you are compiling it because it won't it
won't compile and so you'll you'll get
some kind of error which is really
helpful you know versus you know in a
traditional view if you have like two
angle brackets on one side and just one
on the other you really wouldn't know
until you ran that code right you run it
and then you just get a white screen or
something like that yeah it's like you
got these like weird curly braces and
it's like hello first name yeah oh right
right yeah I want to go a little bit
more into the components we were talking
about earlier what kind of information
is is stored inside a component I
believe in reactors things like props
and State and things like that and I was
wondering if you could go a little bit
more into that yeah absolutely so you
can think of components a lot like
functions at their very base layer
you're gonna have you're gonna create a
component with a function so you say
function my component and then you're
gonna take only one argument and that's
going to be props that's a
object of properties we'll come back to
that but then that component is just
going to return a react element so that
could be a a div that could be a button
it could be any of the HTML elements or
it could be another component now so
going back to those those arguments that
so we have props they always come in as
an object and in props is kind of a mix
of things is going to be all of the
attributes that your component was
called with so that could be ID class
name data attributes all of the regular
HTML attributes are going to be in that
in that bag of props that object of
props and then in addition to that it's
going to be any API that you want to
support so let's say we have a greeting
component and it has a first name and a
last name you join them together or
something like that you would pass those
props into this this object that we get
as an argument as to our component as
HTML style attributes so you know in JSX
we use this using xml type type markup
and it's going to be so you do like
first name equals you know quotes
Michael or Jeremy and then you know last
name you put your last name in and so
now that passes those on to our
component and then the component we're
then merge those together a render
however needs now that's the that's one
interface for managing data in react
that's the that's the first one so just
passing arguments effectively the second
one is with state now the other white
live react is that it's not just a few
layer it does also manage state so you
could write an entire application you
know from from data fetching to you know
to rendering in a react component now a
lot of that's changed over the the
handful of the last year effectively but
components can effectively hold on to
state as well so if you have you know a
simple example of this is just like a
click counter you got a button every
time you tap on it it just increments
number and so that's that state a
component can hold on to that and the
most recent way to do that is through
through hooks you would have these you
have these like kind of like magic
little functions and react that you can
stick inside of your your components
that allow you to hook in to react and
maintain pieces of state so every time
you tap that button you would kind of
tie into this this hook and you know
update it with you know saying hey
increment yourself increment yourself
and then use data returned from that
hook too to render that number it's all
kind of like complicated over over over
voice it's like the react Doc's have
some really good examples specifically
the ones that I mentioned and they show
these are like two liners effectively
but yeah so I'm components can also have
state and that is anytime a component
has state you know it's owned by that
component you know the only way to move
state around would be to have another
component own it and then passing it in
as props or you know use some other type
of global state library that manages all
of that for you but the react method is
to the current one is to use a hook and
just kind of hold it in a in a component
and so just to break it down a little
bit
you said we have props the component is
a is a function so it takes in these
props and those props determine what is
kind of shown inside the component and
then you have state which allows changes
within the component to be persisted for
the duration of I guess for the time the
person is on the page the next thing I
want to talk a little bit about is could
you give us an example of how components
react to changes such as things like
somebody clicking a button or entering
you know information into a text field
how are the components getting notified
of these changes and how is that
information getting to the components
yeah so react has had this long-standing
idea
one way data flow and this is this is
kind of like a big concept I'm not gonna
go into a lot of it right now but that
if you google anything with inputs
you're gonna find you know this term
one-way data flow and so we'll touch on
that a little bit but react has its own
event system and so they call these like
synthetic events so if you wanted to
hook one of these up on your component
let's say you have like a my input and
it's just a you know single input you
could just spit an input out on the page
and it'll behave just like you know any
other other input but the react way of
managing the State for that input field
is you would have an on change you'd put
an on change prop on that thing and you
would give it a function now with hooks
you actually get that function so you if
you used a state hook it would return an
update function and then also the
current state and so you would kind of
hook both of those things up onto your
input so you would say hey on click call
my hook function which updates this
piece of state and then the value is
going to be the piece of state that we
get from that hook so that's kind of
like how we would hook things up in in
react now this gets a little bit
complicated because um first of all you
can just use like the regular regular
inputs without kind of managing the
state but then also many react apps will
use a totally different library to
manage the state of these elements so
you know that might be Redux they might
use a form library specifically that has
its own way of doing it but the the
built-in mechanism is to use some type
of you know use state hook or use
reducer hook and what those do is they
provide you that again they hook into
react they provide you the the current
state and they provide you a function
for updating that state both of it which
you would wire up to your react element
and this gives you the what react
developers kind of referred to as like
this one-way data flow where the
component doesn't update its own value
it calls a function which updates the
state somewhere else and
and uses that return value to to display
the output you know it's it's funny I'm
realizing as we're talking why so many
people find react complicated yeah yeah
I mean it's like the example you're
giving with just a input like a text
input right if someone was building a
traditional form without say a framework
they would type whatever they want to
type into the form and they would submit
it and the browser would kind of
automatically pull out whatever the user
had typed into that field right whereas
it sounds like with react
the typical way you would make that work
is you would have to add an event to the
input field that is basically saying
like call this event every time somebody
types something new into the input field
and then you would have a function that
is being passed in to that component
that is updating its state I guess based
off of these on change events and then
that state would be passed back in to
the component to make the input change
based off of props did I kind of get
that right there okay yeah yeah yeah no
you did get that right and it is all in
in service of kind of protecting that
prop boundary so that things are told
what to do they don't have some secret
knowledge of like how they're hooked up
into the system and so react really does
try very hard to be explicit about
relationships and so having that like
kind of one-way data flow and like
basically asking to update and then
getting your new state via props kind of
allows you to control the application
very fine-grained way now I think you
bring up a really interesting point
because this isn't required this would
be something that would empower you to
make highly interactive forms so like
you know as this piece of state changes
now we're using that data not just to
update the value of the input but maybe
modify some other fields in a different
way if you wanted to just have like a
straight inputs
then have you know on submit' take that
data and do something with it um you can
totally do that as well you could just
have a simple form and then have a you
know form element do on submit and then
give that a function for handling all of
those that entire form when you're done
with it and you could put that in state
if you wanted to or you could you know
just use that data to fire off some type
of you know server query or you know
whatever you want but yeah you could
handle that with a less complex form
doing that just on the the form element
itself so it kind of gives you the
option like they have these ways of
doing it using props and state but if
you decide that you don't want react to
manage that part of your application you
can still use the the regular Dom I
guess and write your app kind of how you
would normally write it totally yeah you
could basically everything in that form
could feel very familiar you don't have
to use any of the special attributes and
then on submit would be the only place
where you're really interacting with
react you say okay this this form is
complete I have all this data now you
know do something with it
got it one of the things people say with
react is that its components are
composable how does react help you build
out your UI and sort of using components
yeah so it's it's really fascinating how
many ways you can compose elements
together when you have the full power of
JavaScript bind you
that's one of my favorite things about
react is because at the end of the day
these elements are an artifact of you
know however you want to compose these
functions together to to make them so
there are a ton of patterns that you can
use to compose components together and
you know the most basic of this of these
is going to be a component that creates
an element from another component so you
have maybe a greeting component and it
just renders an h1 with you know hi your
name well then you can have a header
component the
use that renders that greeting component
along with other components so that
would be a you know the first kind of
form of composition that you can create
components that render other components
so that's that's really handy because
now you only have to do that greeting
once and you can use it in a bunch of
other components to compose new views
together however you can also use
components to compose views and data so
you can have a component that is only
responsible for gathering data so you
say hey when this components rendered go
fetch this data from the the server and
we want you to then take that and render
whatever component we give to you as
props so you could pass a component in
its props and say render this component
with the data that you have so that
would be another way that you could
compose components together now in a way
that allows you to merge data and views
and they're just like a ton of patterns
that you can use for composing these
things together there is an API called
context and what the what context allows
you to do is it allows you to set a
bunch of values that you could use
inside of all of these components by
just like basically just grabbing them
out of the air so it's kind of a third
mechanism for for-4 data so it props
state in context is a way of like
distributing data to a whole tree so I
could say like you know user context I
could create a context for all of the
for my user which has their name their
you know birth date and that favorite
food or something and then when I use
that context when I wrap a certain part
of my subtree in context I can then just
snatch those data those those pieces of
data out of the air in my components
without having to pass them around as
props and this can be a really really
nice way of composing related components
so ones that you know are always going
to have access to certain types of data
and instead of having to pass them
around as props just basically you put
them in the air of this subtree they're
kind of like
local variables to that part of your
application and then they just you can
just grab them out of the air and like
oh hey I know the first name is in the
air somewhere I'm gonna grab that and
use that when I don't have any props so
yeah so these are those are a bunch of
ways that you can you can compose
components together I mean there's
because it's JavaScript there's really
like endless ways that you could compose
components together but those are just
some of the most the most common
composing views of views composing data
and views together and and then also
using context to to create views that
are aware of certain pieces of data kind
of like how with traditional HTML you
know we had tags that could just give us
an input or give us a button and this
sort of is like taking it to the next
step where we could create like you said
a let's say a greeting component or we
can create a survey component we can
create these building blocks that have
not just markup but also have behavior
associated with them and and we can have
a component that's made up of a set of
child components so we kind of get all
these little pieces that we can connect
together when we're building an
application and we can even possibly
reuse components that we used on one
application and use them with another
one yeah absolutely so so one of the
things that I do for my work is I work
on a design system and a component
library that we share between eight
applications and the composability of
react components really comes in handy
for for me in allowing other people to
kind of use the components that they
need without having to do a lot of
customization so if you use something
like bootstrap or bulma a lot of times
they'll have an API that's like button
and then button is link or button is
primary or button is whatever and so all
of these all of these customizations or
modifications exist
inside of the namespace of button now
react kind of
flips that on its head a little bit and
so in a react based component library we
can have the very bottom we can have a
button and the button is basically just
renders out a button attribute and maybe
we do something like type equals button
by default which it should be by default
anyway so we do that and that's our
button component well now we can we can
compose other components over that and
so we can do something like we could
have like a red button and it just like
applies a class or applies some styles
or however we want to do it and now this
is a red button now we don't want to
write like red button everywhere in our
app because you know it's better to
refer to things semantically right like
so maybe this deletes something so then
we can compose that again and we say
like a delete button is a red button
which is a button so kind of it Cascades
a little bit so we have a delete button
is red button is a button now at some
point in the future we say like well
actually we don't want our you know
we've we find red to be offensive we
want it to be something like you know
pink instead well now we can just kind
of like swap that out with pink button
or you know have our delete button just
call button directly or render button
directly and then apply the style
attributes in at once but these are some
really nice tools of being of like
composed swap-out pieces that don't work
for us anymore
without having to overload this base
button with a bunch of props and
knowledge about the entire system very
cool so it's we're building tools that
are not just for the app we're currently
working on it could be something that
could be applied across our company or
it could even be something like let's
say somebody had built like a chart
library or something and that's
something that you could build out and
build an API in terms of what props you
accept and what kinds of functions are
made available and that's something you
could put online and release it as an
open source library and now other people
could use that chart component in you
know their own application that sort of
thing yeah oh absolutely
and and one thing I love about
the react component model is that in
these open-source projects something I'm
seeing a lot is that you know you build
the first version of your chart and it's
gonna have everything is going to be
profit based presumably and the natural
inclination is you know when someone
needs a feature they're going to ask for
a new prop to do that thing and that's
that's great like for a certain period
of time until a year down the road now
you have like 50 props that you could
pass in and it's just super confusing to
use use this library and what I've seen
a lot of people do because of this
composable nature of react is say like
hey instead of giving you extra props
what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna I'm gonna
keep this default interface the way that
it is but what I'm going to do is I'm
going to expose the the inside parts of
this as other components so you need to
change this thing what I'm going to do
is I'm going to give that to you as a
component and then you can change that
thing and then recompose them together
as your own chart so I'm gonna give you
all the pieces that I use to build my
chart and now you have access to those
you can customize them however you want
you could replace them with your own if
you want to and and then build your own
chart from those same composable pieces
and I'm seeing this transformation in a
lot of the react open-source projects
and it's just such a great way to I
guess work in the same sandbox because
you know we've all seen projects start
out with a really simple interface and
then get a really complex you know over
run interface with with a bunch of
customization it's really nice to be
able to just say like hey that that
default interface doesn't work for me so
I'm just gonna pull these pieces out and
then use those to compose my own
interface nice yeah that sounds really
powerful and I have definitely come
across api's and maybe even built some
myself where there's so many kind of
public props or calls where it just is
very difficult to to get started so I
think that's really cool that you can
build with that in mind and kind of
offload some of that to the user of the
component yeah I've seen a lot of people
call this the
calypso I'd like to shift gears a little
bit and talk about how someone can get
started with react first when should a
team consider introducing react like
what kinds of questions should they ask
themselves I think that it depends on
where you're coming from so I can speak
from my experience the team that I work
with we had eight Rails applications and
rails is a great platform and they're
constantly adding to it and a great
framework and they have some really
great tools for kind of managing your
server-side application and then doing
some front-end JavaScript stuff
unfortunately the tools that were
available a handful years ago weren't
great for highly interactive JavaScript
where you make a change over here and
then updates immediately over here that
can be a little bit complicated and
indirect so I think that that was a
natural inflection point for us to say
hey we have these views that are highly
interactive and we want to give the user
immediate feedback that was the point
where we started looking at react
specifically we had an application that
was kind of it was almost like an in
event runner I mean it is an event
runner where you would have this rundown
of all the things that are gonna happen
in an event so think like a meet-up and
you know that you know seven o'clock
someone's given an introduction at 7:15
you got your first talk you got a little
bit of a break for food and then you
know you got your second talk and then
everybody goes home and we had this tool
that would allow you to see the
progression of the event see the
upcoming things it had a real-time chat
hooked up into it you could progress
events if they kind of fired off early
or kind of ran too long or ended ended
early and so there's a very highly
interactive thing and it really wasn't
something that we could do in rails
because these app updates you know with
that we're at least happening every
second so we just decided to go full
bore into to react so this is just a
single react application the nice thing
is it was totally isolated right we just
built a small application and then we
serve it at that route in our rails app
and it was totally isolated from the
rest of our application react hadn't
really we hadn't made a decision to use
react you know across the application we
just said hey this this is a good place
for react and used it that one place and
kind of tried really try really hard to
just kind of like have that it be a
decision point for the rest of the app
like do we need it do we need to have
high interactivity in this application
do we have an endpoint that we're
interacting with already set up those
are some questions that I found really
helpful in deciding whether or not it
was time to embrace react now it's you
know five or six years later and I think
that that that decision point is maybe
moved up a little bit I think there's a
lot of people who are starting in you
know or their app is already very heavy
on the client-side I think that that is
gonna be a little bit more of a
difficult question you know if you let's
say you already have an ember app or you
already have an angular app when do you
make the decision to you know maybe give
react to try I couldn't I couldn't
answer that one per se but I would say
find a piece that can can be completely
owned by react and just start there and
see how it feels and see if that can
naturally grow into other parts of the
application and in this example that
you're giving did you use react to
control an entire page or was it a
traditional server rendered page that
had react components and parts of it
yeah so this was the the first
experimenting with react was it is just
it was just a page so we had a rails
route and that route just had that
single Dom node and we said hey react
render yourself here and the whole
application was basically just one
gigantic component because this was you
know five or six years ago we didn't
understand how the composition work
I mean I don't think the industry really
understood composition so we had this I
mean I think it was maybe like a 1500
line component with maybe another 2,000
lines of of mix-ins which was an API
that they had at the time to basically
force and other components into your
component thank god they've gotten rid
of it now yeah so it was probably like
it was effectively like a 3,000 line
component Wow
I guess one thing I would ask is if
somebody is in sort of a similar
situation where they have a traditional
server rendered page and there's a
portion of that page that has some kind
of complicated user interaction like for
example let's say you have a page that
that has a form that is very complicated
and you want to do a lot of client-side
validation that sort of thing hmm would
you take the approach you did where the
route just had a single Dom node that
react kind of took over or would you
have the majority of the page still be a
rendered traditionally and then just
make that one form or that one section
be made with react components yeah
that's a great question so one of the
cool things is that because react only
needs a Dom node
I think either approach is valid and the
that that second approach that you
mentioned is what we ended up taking in
a lot of other places in our application
once we decided that react was a good
fit for a company we would basically say
like hey this one like you said this
form is highly interactive and we want
to be able to control that and give
immediate feedback to the user and so we
would just render a Dom node there that
we could you know render our react
application to and then you know just do
that and it was you know in the context
of a rails rendered view everything else
had remained the same but we were able
to just kind of convert that one node in
this interactive form and I think that's
a that's a great approach as well when
you're sort of making that decision what
are some of the pros and cons of taking
the isolated
and strategy versus having react take
care of the entire page who I know from
me I don't like to rewrite stuff rewrite
the same code in a different language so
so for me I would be hard pressed to
want to just take that entire view one
that's already working one that's
already tested and then convert the
whole thing just because so for me I
always like to take the smallest
possible chunk and then have it
naturally grow and I think that's one
thing I really love about react is that
well some frameworks are very
opinionated you know they need to be
they need to control the whole page
react is not and you know one of the
beautiful things of that is is that you
can decide how much of your application
you have to rewrite to get the
interactive parts that you want so yeah
I would always recommend you know if
you're doing any type of transformation
react or not to start with the smallest
amount of the smallest piece possible
and and then kind of like see how that
grows I know some people really can't
handle the incongruity of that but I
don't know I would I would just
recommend you know training yourself to
- to have more of that in your life
because every application has has some
degree of that and being able to live
with you know different mindsets and you
know different frameworks is just kind
of part of working on and valuable
production code yeah so I guess you
would say to basically be very targeted
like start small if you have something
that's working just change the part that
you think could use that extra
interactivity and don't worry so much
about having to sort of be between two
worlds I guess you know having having to
understand the the rails view as well as
the react view you don't consider that
to be an issue you think that's
something that most people will have to
deal with yeah well I think there's a
lot of things that we just we just don't
think about when we are inclined toward
a rewrite so you know some of those
things are you know maybe a lot of that
view is already tested and so now you
have to redo all of those
Tess you know it's and so it's not just
changing the view you're changing the
tests and then also you know in the case
of moving from something like rails to
react those tests are changing
frameworks and approaches and I think
that those types of things we tend to I
guess like brush out of our mind when
we're thinking about oh it would be fun
to redo this thing in react we forget
about all the things that wrap that view
that we've already established and you
know I think those are the things that
kind of come back to bite us at that
like 80% mark you know we've already got
we've got all the functionality but now
we have to backfill all the tests that
we've you know deleted now and all that
kind of and that's like that part is
just like soul-crushing when you get
there you're like oh man we've we've
made a mistake
totally I mean it's when you you have
something that works you know especially
if it's been a while and you've
established like you know we put this
stuff out we have our tests it's been
running in production and you know we're
good like that's that's something very
powerful right and you don't really want
to give that up
oh for sure so another thing I'd like to
ask about is if you have something like
a Google Maps page that's not built in
react does it still make sense to use
react in your application for that page
like how would you approach that oh yeah
that's it that's a great question so
react does have some escape hatches for
you to be able to render some type of
JavaScript thing you know so in this
case a map that isn't react and to be
able to to render that without having it
having to re-implement it and react and
so there's there's a few api's for this
depending on what you need but
effectively you can kind of force
something into any of these notes so
there's some videos on egghead that I've
seen where people are demonstrating how
you could use jQuery UI Calendar widgets
inside of
and it might be a little bit too
complicated to try to you know verbalize
over-the-air sure there are escape
hatches for that yeah I know that one of
them was it dangerously set innerhtml
so you so there's an API that you can
use that allows you to basically just
tell a node in react a this is the HTML
you have to render as react we're not
controlling it we're just giving you a
big string and you're going to render
that into the Dom so that's one of the
escape hatches that you can use
sometimes you can use the lifecycle
events to basically you know give the
thing an ID and then render render
whatever it is that you need to to that
ID once it's already in the establish to
be in the Dom depending on what approach
you need to take and what the lifecycle
of the library you're using is there
they're absolutely approaches that you
can use to kind of encapsulate that into
a component as like the jQuery UI
calendar react component that just pops
out and uses jQuery UI mm-hmm next I'd
like to talk about how to get started
with react because I think react like
you've sort of been saying throughout
our conversation a lot of times people
say it's just the view layer but I think
what people often find out is to get
started with react there's all these
other things they have to learn or
there's all these starter kits that
people recommend and so it can get
really overwhelming so how would you
recommend someone get started like what
are the things they should focus on yeah
that's a great question one of my
favorite tools today is called code
sandbox and code sandbox is totally set
up out of the they have a playground for
react apps and everything that you need
to get started is in there so if you
want to just start playing with react
and you know that you're gonna have some
trouble you know getting getting you
know babble set up for JSX and and all
of those things that are kind of side
effects of playing with react if you
just want
play with it and get a sense of it code
sandbox is amazing we have a react
project you just click a button and then
boom you're set up in a react app you
can then go through all the tutorials
you can follow along in the
documentation it's amazing so that's
that's the first thing then you can do
pretty much anything that you would do
you can you know you can npm install
different packages you can make requests
to to various data services and it's
it's really good when I do trainings I
will usually use code sandbox because it
takes all of the setup out of it beyond
that there's a couple starters that I
think are better than others
Facebook maintains a project called to
create react app unfortunately it does
require that you have at least a base
level command of node because all of
this stuff happens in a node process in
fact the code sandbox starter is based
on create react app so the next step
would be you know to go from you know
your code sandbox starter to create
react app because the same environment
effectively but now you have to use node
so you'd have to install node you'd have
to kind of get a sense of NPM install
and NPM installing a create react app
fortunately they've made it very easy
but I'd say that that's one of the next
best places to go because it's kind of
spiritually connected to the code
sandbox they've made it easy the
documentation is great and all those
things like you know JSX
and things that you might not even think
of you know if you want to load an SVG
or you want to load styles from CSS or
something else
all of those are taken care of they've
given you well-documented nice API is
they've they've connected all done all
the connective tissue to make sure that
that works for you and then the third
thing is something that I use all the
time I don't I don't personally use
create react app when I'm starting a
project but there's a company called
site and they have a project called next
j/s and it's it's kind of a static site
generator kind of but I find it to be
the easiest way to actually like just
get started with react and I really love
neck
it's like a the NPM installed two things
and now everything in anything that you
put in pages directory becomes like a
react page and you can do do all kinds
of cool stuff with that so that's one of
my my that's my personal favorite
starting point with with react but code
Santa box definitely give that a try and
create react app is probably your next
step once you've you've decided to make
the jump into using using a little bit
of node to control your your app build
and earlier you had talked about how
when you and your team first started
using react it was in the context of an
existing server rendered application
would you be able to use a create react
app or next yes in combination with that
or what would be the approach for
someone in that situation yeah so a lot
of frameworks will have some type of
plug-in or gem or you know whatever the
the mechanism is for your framework to
connect a react app so so rails I know
has generators now by default where you
can generate a react app review app or L
map inside of rails I am not too
familiar with the other frameworks but I
imagine that now it's it's probably
pretty simple in a lot of the major
frameworks like you know Python or net
to get started with a with some type of
generated rails can react configuration
another thing I'd like to ask is when
someone is learning react there are
going to be a lot of resources they see
that use features that maybe aren't
widely used anymore or maybe have better
alternatives now what are the things
that someone should avoid when they're
looking at tutorials and looking up
guides what what are the features that
they maybe don't need to consider
anymore so the last year has marked a
lot of change and a lot of that change
is around hooks so I'd mentioned hooks
earlier in our conversation
but hooks are really the the new like do
it all kind of collection of api's in
react so react has had a lot of I guess
ways of defining components and right
now the the the the happy path is you
just do function style components so
it's just a function that wraps a you
know a react element and now when you
want to do things like you know
connected data or have some kind of side
effect where you maybe change a class
outside of your react app in the Dom or
you know using context which which we
talked about earlier using state all of
these kinds of things are now wrapped up
in hooks and the beauty of hooks is that
you can use them in function components
which are the simplest to define it's
just a function that would create
returns a react element and now you can
just use these you can you know connect
to state you can connect to the outside
world and update classes or whatever you
want to do connect to data and all of
that can happen in hooks now that used
to be a lot more complicated when we had
a class API for defining components and
you had to know a bunch of life cycle
methods to kind of connect to state and
whatnot so if you don't have to if
you're not working in a legacy app that
is using the class component api's I
think that really using the functional
style components and react hooks is is
where you want to be push as hard as you
can to be living in that Wonderland
because those api's are great they're so
well thought out they're much easier to
use and if you're just starting out
right now I wouldn't even bother with
the other ones because you know so many
libraries now are using hooks it's
really a lot you can get very far
without even having to learn the other
the the class style and kind of all the
resulting methods of composing
components that were birthed out of that
so yeah so function components hooks
and yeah I would just I would just start
with that do everything you can in that
and then I know that you know sometime
over the next year there's gonna be a
new API called Spence or I think it
exists now but nobody's really using it
because the tools aren't there to use it
but that is going to be the best way to
connect to data and it's it's really
geared around giving users or great
experiences when they're waiting for
data or when those requests fail and you
know that's a conversation for another
time because it's you know it's all
still being figured out but suspense is
going to be the way to connect to data
in the future and it it looks amazing to
basically summarize like a lot of the
things that people will be dealing with
are going to be props and state and
context and you said basically to look
for solutions that use hooks for all of
those things and avoid things that are
using say class components at this point
yeah I think so much of the the react
world is going to there there's there's
been a couple people who've gone on
record saying that look there's gonna be
two eras of react you know the pre hooks
and post hooks and I think that's true I
think that they have found the the
missing piece to really simplify a lot
of our app code and yeah if you're
getting started today you're just gonna
be delighted by how easy hooks are
compared to maybe every other time
you've looked at react another thing is
there are a lot of libraries for things
like routing or authentication things
where when somebody is building their
application using react they may not
know where to start
so are there like a list of recommended
libraries or components that you
recommend people use when they're first
getting started yeah so react router is
great I think that you know they've
they've put a lot of care into that and
there's a blog post now I know there was
a little bit of a split for a moment and
there's a there was a reach
and they're they've they're working
together again to make the next version
of react router but yeah that's kind of
the de facto choice as far as routing
goes there are a bunch of styling
libraries I'd say that if you if you
really want to avoid writing CSS which
you don't have to I write CSS all the
time I love it there are some styling
libraries the most popular ones are
styled components and emotion so those
are the two they're I'm trying to think
about like what else I would like
recommend across the board I mean really
once I have a router once I have some
styling solution if you have the option
of using a graph QL endpoint Apollo does
seem to be Apollo client seems to be the
the one that everyone loves in terms of
connecting to connecting to a graph QL
datasource so yeah you probably have to
figure out how to how to connect to data
there's a bunch of components out there
that allow you to use a hook or whatnot
to fetch data from a restful endpoint as
well
I couldn't say that there's like a
universal winner but there are a bunch
out there yeah I think that would be you
know that'd be my starting point I liked
it I like to keep it really simple but
you know react router is a must for me
so start with something like create rack
tap or next J s and then the router and
InStyle components and Apollo if you're
using graph QL and basically just start
with that and don't worry about anything
else like get started with those and see
what you can build with that oh yeah
absolutely and and one cool thing about
next is that actually has a router built
in so because it uses the file system is
like an API for four routes any
additional folders that you put into the
pages directory get their own routes and
so you actually don't think about
routing at all and it works on server
side or client it's um it's pretty
amazing so like when I don't want to
think about routing I just use next and
it's it does everything that I want one
thing that I did want to touch on that I
get a lot of questions about is when
people are learning react they often
also start learning Redux or think they
need to start learning Redux I wanted to
kind of get your thoughts on
whether that's something people should
look at or whether that's something
that's overkill kind of what your
thoughts are on yeah I can only say that
I have never used Redux so I've built a
ton of applications and for me just the
the state management in react was enough
so I think that you can get really far
without using Redux one of the really
neat things about Reid there's two
really cool things about Redux and you
know one is it really teaches you how to
use how to manage state with immutable
concepts and so I think there's some
really good valuable lessons to learn
there from Redux and then the second
thing is there's a huge community around
Redux so there's a ton of middleware
that already exists that you can just
kind of npm install and take advantage
of and there's some great developer
tools that you can take advantage of but
I feel like if you're not going to take
advantage of those Redux can be
extremely cumbersome and I think
ultimately the the thing that Redux you
know gave us four years ago has
effectively been brought into react via
context and there's a use reducer hook
so those were really the two core
innovations of redux and those exist in
in reacts now as first class documented
you know components so I really don't
think that I mean personally different
from my experience I really don't think
that people should jump into react and
redux at the same time like I think that
that's always a bad idea people don't
really get a good sense of where the
boundaries are when they when they do
them simultaneously however I don't
think Redux is bad if it is a good fit
for your team and it provides you with
with structures that help you build
better software then I think that's
great but I think that you know I think
that there's a lot of stuff and react
now that I would maybe try as a first
first step and then kind of see if you
know you need to take that next step in
redux nice
the last thing I'd like to kind of sum
up with is testing with react components
how is testing and react different than
how front-end testing has traditionally
been done yeah I would say it's it's not
markedly different I think that anytime
you have like you know asynchronous
behaviors you really have to do you have
to use some kind of framework that's you
know integrated yes to use some type of
testing framework that's at least a
little bit integrated with the library
itself so it knows when those events
have have resolved I know for me I don't
personally do a lot of like application
testing I would say I can't see dodds
has a really great course I think it's
just like testing JavaScript or
something calm he's done a bunch to
really like dive into that space I know
for me I usually like to test even
though it's a little bit slower I like
to test from like the most outside point
when I'm doing views so I use Cypress
which is just an end-to-end tester it
basically just fires up your app in a
browser and you know it has and you just
kind of look say hey this thing is here
focus it type this thing and hit submit
and you know what what resulted that's
the approach that I typically like to
take just because I know it's the most
failsafe in terms of mapping to the
experience the users going to get but
you know this trade-offs a lot of people
like to test a little bit closer to you
know the components and that's that's
fine too
awesome so to kind of wrap up do you
have any questions I didn't ask or any
advice you'd like to give oh man you
know I think just have fun I know that
there's so much material out there and a
lot of it comes from different eras of
react and that can be really challenging
to navigate I think that if you stick to
stuff that helps you with functional
compunction components and hooks you're
gonna be you're gonna have a really good
experience so the documentation is
really good I recommend you know
checking it out there I have a show
called
react podcast and I try as much as I can
to have it be beginner friendly and
we have you know a lot of experts
talking about all kinds of stuff so you
know graph QL hooks react router a bunch
of stuff that applies to open source
like versioning animation in react
we just had some episodes on that and
yeah so if you if you're interested in
react and hearing from a lot of people
who are kind of making it happen I think
that that's that's where I do a lot of
my learning and so hopefully other
people can learn along with me yeah I've
listened to a lot of the episodes in it
it's really a great resource I mean you
get to hear from the people who are
basically building the future of react
or building the components building the
libraries and you really learn a lot
awesome awesome well thanks finally so
how can people follow you or follow the
react podcast yeah so I am fantastic on
on Twitter I guess and some other places
I've started doing a little bit more
writing on dev to I'm trying to get in
with that community yeah chan chan
tastic on twitter is probably the the
best connection point I link to a lot of
my my writing I have a small resource
called
react patterns that I'm going to be kind
of reworking to or its react patterns
calm I'm gonna be reworking that to
start showing off hooks and so hopefully
that'll be it's been a really helpful
resource to get some newcomers in to
react in the past and I'm hoping that I
can refresh it to be that same resource
for people today awesome well Michael
thank you so much for coming on the show
thank you so much for having me Jeremy
this has been super fun this has been
Jeremy Jung for a software engineering
radio thank you for listening thanks for
listening to se radio an educational
program brought to you by Triple E
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at SE - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at se radio.com
you can also email us a team at SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
SU radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening